A Guide to the Joe Miller Collection, 1960-2003
Digital Library and Archives, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Digital Library and Archives, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Joe Miller Collection, 1960-2003
Digital Library and Archives, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2007-801
2 flip top document boxes; 1 cu. ft.
The Joe Miller Collection consists of materials relating to Miller's work on the development and implementation of bar codes for the retail industry. The collection consists mainly of manuals and handbooks relating to the implementation of standardized inventory control systems in the retail industry.
Joe Miller
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Joe Miller Collection was donated to the Digital Library and Archives in 2007.
Biographical Information
Joe Miller was most well-known for being a pioneer in implementing the bar code system in retail stores. He was born in Richmond, VA and served in the Navy during the second World War. After the war, he took a job at Thalhimer's Department Stores in Richmond where he helped to create a computer system to track inventory. Later, he took a job working for the National Retail Merchants Association(NRMA) as the director of retail standards and technology. There Miller worked on the implementation of bar code systems. Joe Miller died in April of 2003 at the age of 82.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of materials concerned with the implementation of inventory control systems in the retail industry. These materials include proposals, manuals, and handbooks related to inventory controls systems like the bar code. There are also manuals relating to creation of merchandise classifications and implementation of code systems. Also included with the collection are two obituaries giving information about Miller's life as a bar code pioneer as well as personal information.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Univac Proposal for Thalhimer Brothers, c.1960 (Box-folder 1:1-2)
- Universal Vendor Marketing, 1976 (Box-folder 1:3)
- Merchandise Planning and Control, 1982-1984 (Box-folder 1:4)
- Emporium Group Holdings, Introduction to Merchandising, 1983 (Box-folder 1:5-6)
- NRMA X-12 Information, Vol. 1, 1986 (Box-folder 1:7)
- Krieger, Murray. The Complete Dictionary for Buying and Merchandising, National Retail Merchants Assocation: New York, 1987 (Box-folder 2:1)
- Voluntary Interindustry Communications Standards - Retail Industry Conventions and Implementation Guidelines, June 1987 (Box-folder 2:2)
- EDI Data Segments and Data Elements, Vol. 4, 1987 (Box-folder 2:3)
- Standard Color and Size Code Handbook, National Retail Merchants Association: New York, 1988 (Box-folder 2:4)
- EBDI - ANSI ASC 12 Standards - Slide Presentation, 1991 (Box-folder 2:5)
- X12/DISA Information Manual, 1991 (Box-folder 2:6)
- NRF Reports - After Retirement, 1991 and n.d. (Box-folder 2:7)
- Obituaries, 2003 (Box-folder 2:8)